{"test_questions": [[{"question": "A cycloconverter can be", "opta": "step down", "optb": "step up", "optc": "step down or step up", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The output frequency can be more or less than input frequency."}, {"question": "In the below figure the average load current is 15 A. The rms value of transformer secondary current is", "opta": "15 A", "optb": "10.61 A", "optc": "7.5 A", "optd": "14.14 A", "ans": "B", "explanation": "RMS secondary current =  = 15/1.414 = 10.608 A."}, {"question": "In a 3 phase fully controlled converter the firing frequency is", "opta": "3 times the line frequency", "optb": "6 times the line frequency", "optc": "9 times the line frequency", "optd": "12 times the line frequency", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is a 6 pulse converter."}, {"question": "Two thyristor of same rating and same specifications", "opta": "will have equal turn on and turn off periods", "optb": "will have equal turn on but unequal turn off periods", "optc": "may have equal or unequal turn on and turn off periods", "optd": "will have unequal turn on and turn off periods", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Turn on and turn off times of similar SCRs may not be same."}, {"question": "The amount of dielectric heating is inversely proportional to frequency.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It is proportional to frequency."}, {"question": "A semiconverter feeding an RLE load operates in", "opta": "first quadrant only", "optb": "first and second quadrants", "optc": "first and fourth quadrants", "optd": "first and third quadrants", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Semiconvertor operates only in first quadrant."}, {"question": "The phenomenon of overlap in converter operation due to", "opta": "source resistance", "optb": "source inductance", "optc": "both source resistance and source inductance", "optd": "high value of firing angle", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Source inductance delays turn off and hence causes overlap."}, {"question": "A thyristor has a maximum allowable junction temperature of 120\u00b0C and the ambient temperature is 40\u00b0C. If thermal resistance is 1.6\u00b0 C/W, the maximum allowable internal power dissipation is", "opta": "20 W", "optb": "50 W", "optc": "92 W", "optd": "128 W", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For a 12 pulse operation, the two 6 pulse units are fed by", "opta": "Y - Y and Y - Y transformers", "optb": "\u0394 - \u0394 and \u0394 - \u0394 transformers", "optc": "Y - Y and Y - \u0394 transformers", "optd": "Y - \u0394 and Y - \u0394 transformers", "ans": "C", "explanation": "30\u00b0 phase difference is necessary."}, {"question": "In a single phase full wave converter (M - 2 connection) feeding a highly inductive load, the firing angle for each thyristor is a in the respective half cycle. The period of conduction of each thyristor is", "opta": "p - a", "optb": "p", "optc": "p + a", "optd": "p - 2a", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since conduction is from a to p + a, period of conduction is p in each half cycle."}, {"question": "An SCR is triggered at 40\u00b0 in the positive half cycle only. The average anode current is 50 A. If the firing angle is changed to 80\u00b0, the average anode current is likely to be", "opta": "50 A", "optb": "25 A", "optc": "less than 50 A but more than 25 A", "optd": "less than 25 A", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The characteristics of a non-linear resistance is i = kv4. If i becomes 100 times, v becomes", "opta": "about 100 times", "optb": "about 10 times", "optc": "about 3 times", "optd": "about twice", "ans": "C", "explanation": "v \u221d (i)1/4 \u221d (100)1/4 \u2248 3."}, {"question": "In a step down chopper using pulse width modulation, Ton = 3 x 10-3 and Toff = 1 x 10-3 s. The chopping frequency is", "opta": "333.33", "optb": "250", "optc": "500", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "Thyristors are suitable for dc circuit breakers but not for ac circuit breakers.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "They are suitable for both dc and ac circuit breakers."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Inverters and choppers use fast switching thyristors Reason (R):  Fast switching SCR has low turn off time.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Low turn off time enables fast switching."}, {"question": "The value of capacitor C for dynamic equalising circuit of series connected thyristors is determined by", "opta": "forward characteristics of thyristors", "optb": "reverse recovery characteristics of thyristors", "optc": "both forward and reverse recovery characteristics of thyristors", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Value of C is proportional to maximum difference between reverse charge of SCRs in series."}, {"question": "A chopper", "opta": "converts constant voltage dc into ac and then into variable voltage dc", "optb": "converts constant voltage dc into variable voltage dc directly", "optc": "converts ac of one frequency into ac of another frequency", "optd": "converts ac to dc", "ans": "B", "explanation": "A chopper is a dc-ac converter. It converts a fixed dc voltage into a variable dc voltage."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  If the duty cycle of chopper is low the current would not become discontinuousReason (R):  If the time constant L/R of the load in chopper is low the current may become discontinuous.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "C", "explanation": "If duty cycle is low, current may become discontinuous."}, {"question": "In a single phase full wave regulator, the firing angles in the positive and negative half cycles are generally", "opta": "equal", "optb": "different", "optc": "equal or different", "optd": "different but sometimes equal", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Firing angles are kept equal to get symmetrical output voltage."}, {"question": "An electric heater is controlled by thyristors through on-off control. If a = 0.4, the heating is", "opta": "16% maximum", "optb": "40% of maximum", "optc": "60% of maximum", "optd": "84% of maximum", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Vl = V a. Therefore Vl2 - V2 (a). Heating is proportional to a."}, {"question": "A two winding transformer is feeding a single phase half wave rectifier circuit. The load is purely resistive. The rms value of transformer secondary current is Is and rms value of load current in Irms. Then", "opta": "Is = Irms irrespective of the value of firing angle", "optb": "Is = 0.5 Irms irrespective of the value of firing angle", "optc": "Is = Irms if firing angle is less than 30\u00b0", "optd": "Is = Irms if firing angle is more than 30\u00b0", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "The terminals of a power BJT are called", "opta": "emitter, base, collector", "optb": "emitter, base, drain", "optc": "source, base, drain", "optd": "source, base, collector", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a BJT terminals are emitter, base and collector irrespective of rating."}, {"question": "In single phase half wave regulator, the average current over one full cycle", "opta": "is always positive", "optb": "may be positive or negative", "optc": "may be negative", "optd": "is always negative", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The input current during positive half cycle is less than that during negative half cycle."}, {"question": "The dynamic equalising circuit consists of a series combination of capacitor C and resistor RC across each thyristor. This resistance RC (along with parallel connected diode)", "opta": "limits charging current", "optb": "limits discharging current", "optc": "limits both charging and discharging currents", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Discharge current flows through Re ."}, {"question": "A single phase semiconverter is feeding a highly inductive load and has freewheeling diode across the load. The waveshapes of output voltage and output current", "opta": "are similar", "optb": "are not similar", "optc": "may be similar or dissimilar", "optd": "are similar only if firing angle is zero", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When freewheeling diode conducts output current exists but output voltage is zero."}, {"question": "Current derating may be necessary when thyristors are operating in", "opta": "series", "optb": "parallel", "optc": "series or parallel", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since current does not divide equally, current derating is necessary."}, {"question": "If duty cycle is a and the load is a resistance R, the rms value of output voltage is", "opta": "aV", "optb": "a V", "optc": "a2V", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "RMS output voltage\nVL = a V."}, {"question": "For a BJT a = 0.98, then \u03b2 =", "opta": "0.02", "optb": "0.5", "optc": "4.9", "optd": "48", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Power transistor has lower switching time than SCR Reason (R):  Power transistor has greater switching time than SCR", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Power transistor does not have high  rating."}, {"question": "A 3 kV circuit uses SCR of 800 V rating. If derating is 25%, the number of SCRs in series is", "opta": "4", "optb": "5", "optc": "6", "optd": "8", "ans": "B", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a circuit using a full wave converter (M - 2 connection) the PIV of each thyristor is 400 V. For the same output voltage and fully controlled bridge converter, PIV will be", "opta": "400 V", "optb": "800 V", "optc": "200 V", "optd": "2002 V", "ans": "C", "explanation": "In bridge connection PIV is half of that in M-2 connection."}, {"question": "A dc separately excited motor has constant field current. The armature is fed from a single phase supply through a full converter. When a = 0, speed is 500 rpm. If a = 45\u00b0, the speed is likely to be", "opta": "about 350 rpm", "optb": "about 250 rpm", "optc": "about 175 rpm", "optd": "about 125 rpm", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Average output voltage \u221d cos a and therefore reduced to 0.707 of the value for a = 0. Speed is nearly proportional to voltage."}, {"question": "In a multiphase chopper, all choppers operate together.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "They operate in a sequence."}, {"question": "The terminals of a power MOSFET are called", "opta": "emitter, base, collector", "optb": "source, gate, drain", "optc": "source, base, drain", "optd": "emitter, gate, drain", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In a MOSFET terminals are source, gate, drain irrespective of rating."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  The surge current which an SCR can withstand is much higher than rms on state current.Reason (R):  The duration of surge current is very small.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since duration of surge current is small, the associated energy is small."}, {"question": "A single phase half wave controlled rectifier circuit has a free wheeling diode. The load is a combination of R and L. The firing angle is a. The period of conduction of SCR and free wheeling diode respectively are", "opta": "a < \u03c9t < p and p < \u03c9t < (2p + a)", "optb": "a < \u03c9t < p and p < \u03c9t < 2p", "optc": "a < \u03c9t < (p + a) and (p + a) < \u03c9t < 2p", "optd": "a < \u03c9t < p and p < \u03c9t < (2p - a)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "SCR conducts from a to p and free wheeling diode from p to (2p + a)."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A transistor requires a continuous base signal for conduction but a thyristor requires a gate pulse.Reason (R):  Transistor find widespread application in power electronic circuits.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Transistors are used but not very widely."}, {"question": "In a thyristor the gate current is increased, then", "opta": "anode current will increase", "optb": "anode current will decrease", "optc": "anode current will remain constant", "optd": "anode current may increase or decrease", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Gate current does not affect the magnitude of anode current."}, {"question": "Thyristors are not suitable for logic circuits.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Thyristors can be used for logic circuits."}, {"question": "A single phase half wave rectifier is feeding a resistive load. Input voltage v = Vm sin \u03c9t. The output dc voltage is Vdc and output rms voltage is Vrms . If firing angle is 180\u00b0, Vdc and Vrms respectively are", "opta": "0 and 0", "optb": "", "optc": "0 and - Vm", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Put a = 180\u00b0 in Eqs  \nOtherwise also a = 180\u00b0 means no conduction. \nHence zero output voltage."}, {"question": "The number of leads in an SCR are :", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Anode, cathode and gate."}, {"question": "In a single phase full wave converter (M-2 connection) feeding on R - L load, the input voltage is v = Vm sin \u03c9t. The expression for dc output voltage is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Due to inductive load the period of conduction is a to p + a in each half cycle."}, {"question": "A thyristor has a turn on time of 6 \u03bcs. If the anode circuit is inductive, the turn on time will be", "opta": "6 \u03bcs", "optb": "less than 6\u03bcs", "optc": "more than 6 \u03bcs", "optd": "either 6 \u03bcs or less", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Inductive load increases the turn on time."}, {"question": "The total number of leads in reverse conducting thyristor is", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "1", "optd": "4", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  A TRIAC is a bidirectional SCR.Reason (R):  A TRIAC is a four layers 3 terminal device and can conduct in both directions.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Since a TRIAC can conduct in both directions it is bi directional SCR."}, {"question": "If Vdc1 is the dc output voltage in half wave controlled rectifier circuit feeding resistive load and Vdc2 is the dc output voltage in full wave controlled rectifier circuit (M - 2 connection) feeding resistive load, then", "opta": "Vdc1 = 0.5 Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "optb": "Vdc1 = Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "optc": "Vdc1 \u2264 0.5 Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "optd": "Vdc1 \u2265 0.5 Vdc2 for all values of firing angle", "ans": "A", "explanation": "and Vdc =  (1 + cos a)."}, {"question": "A semi converter operates in two quadrants.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "It operates only in quadrant."}, {"question": "Figure shows a chopper feeding RLE load, The free wheeling diode conducts when", "opta": "thyristor is on", "optb": "thyristor is off", "optc": "both when thyristor is on and thyristor is off", "optd": "partly when thyristor is off and partly when thyristor is on", "ans": "B", "explanation": "FD is forward biased only when thyristor is off."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  An ideal rectifier should have unity harmonic factorReason (R):  An ideal rectifier should have unity displacement factor.", "opta": "Both A and R are correct and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R correct but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is correct but R is wrong", "optd": "A is wrong but R is correct", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Ideal rectifier should have zero harmonic factor and unity displacement factor."}, {"question": "A single phase half wave rectifier is feeding a resistive load. When a = 0, dc output voltage is 127 V. When a = 30\u00b0, the dc output voltage will be about", "opta": "127 V", "optb": "120 V", "optc": "110 V", "optd": "100 V", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Using Eq  \n = 0.933. \nHence Vdc for 30\u00b0 firing angle = 0.933 x 127 = \u2248 120 V."}]]}